Guide to the William Garrott Brown Papers, 1898-1917 RL.10105
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Garrott Brown papers
1898-1917
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Brown, William Garrott
RL.10105
2 Linear Feet 4 boxes, 1,013 items (inc. 2 vols.)
This collection contains personal and professional correspondence and literary notes of historian and essayist William Garrott Brown. The letters center around Brown's literary work and friends, but also discuss Republican politics in the South, political reaction to the imperialistic policies of Theodore Roosevelt and support of Woodrow Wilson, and the passage of the Aldrich monetary bill, which formed the basis of Federal Reserve System. It also includes letters from Brown to John Spencer Bassett giving biographical information. Other correspondents include many promiment literary and political figures. Additional papers include copies of Brown's letters in the Charles William Eliot Papers, Harvard University, and the Edward Mandell House Papers, Yale University. These concern race relations and Woodrow Wilson's 1912 presidential campaign.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Biographical Note
William Garrott Brown was a historian, biographer, and essayist, of Marion, Alabama, and Cambridge, Massachusetts who graduated from Harvard College in 1891.
Provenance
The William Garrott Brown papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1933.
Collection Overview
This collection consists of mostly letters that center around William Garrott Brown's literary work and friends; the efforts of so-called Southern liberals to make the Republican party respectable in the South; the attempts of liberals of the nation to halt the imperialistic policies of Theodore Roosevelt by supporting Woodrow Wilson; and maneuvering behind the passing of the Aldrich monetary bill, which formed the basis of the Federal Reserve System. Also included are letters to John Spencer Bassett giving biographical information on Brown, Brown's diploma from Harvard, a copy of his will and letters from editors of Harper's Weekly and the Youth's Companion.
Additional papers include copies of Brown's letters collected by Bruce Clayton while writing his dissertation. They are in part reproduced from the Charles William Eliot Papers, Harvard University Library, and relate to Brown's career, the Harvard Guide to American History, Southern feelings toward Harvard and Massachusetts, and race relations. Other Brown letters reproduced by Clayton from the Edward Mandell House Papers, Yale University Library, concern Woodrow Wilson's presidential campaign, 1912.
Among the correspondents are: Charles Francis Adams, Edwin A. Alderman, Frederic Bancroft, J. S. Bassett, Gamaliel Bradford, William Garrott Brown (including some copies), W. L. Courtney (of the English Fortnightly Review), William A. Dunning, William Preston Few, W. W. Finley, Walter L. Fleming, Richard W. Gilder, Carter Glass, Edmund W. Gosse, Gilliam Grissom, Norman Hapgood, T. P. Harrison, Harper and Brothers, A. B. Hart, Hamilton Holt, A. E. Holton, E. M. House, D. F. Houston, J. F. Jameson, J. N. Lamed, Henry Cabot Lodge, Hamilton W. Mabie, S. W. McCall, A. C. McLaughlin, Shailer Mathews, John M. Morehead, John T. Morgan, David A. Munro, S. N. D. North, Charles E. Norton, Walter Hines Page, Bliss Perry, Herbert Putnam, James Ford Rhodes, Theodore Roosevelt, D. C. Roper, H. E. Scudder, Ellery Sedgwick, Thomas Settle, James T. Shotwell, H. L. Stimson, Moorfield Storey, F. W. Taussig, William R. Thayer, Frank B. Tracy, Oscar W. Underwood, Booker T. Washington, and Woodrow Wilson (copies).
Historians -- Correspondence; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1912; United States -- Politics and government -- 1909-1913; Currency question -- United States; United States -- Race relations; Wilson, Woodrow; Brown, William Garrott; Bassett, John Spencer, 1867-1928; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Roosevelt, Theodore
- William Garrott Brown papers, 1898-1917
  - Harvard diploma, 1891 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1900-1910; 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1911-1912; 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1913-1917 and undated; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence of Bruce Clayton with Alabama sources, 1962 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence (copies), 1911-1913 (Box 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Photocopies from the Edward Mandell House papers at Yale.
  - Correspondence (copies), 1892-1909 (Box 3)
    Photocopies of papers of Charles W. Eliot of Harvard University.
  - The South at Work (photocopy), 1904 (Box 4)
  - Notes, undated (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1912-1913 (Box 4)
    Clippings from Harper's Weekly